Abraham: There has been a significant
growth in cyber criminality over the last
few years especially with ransomware.
Breaches of personal data
leaves victims vulnerable to
fraud and puts lives at risk.
Business is the main target although
phishing attacks on individuals
are increasing, however more people
are becoming aware of the threat.
On a global scale governments and
nations are also at high risk of falling
victim to cyber crime in one way or
another and this affects everyone.
Nicole: Cybercrime is a
violation of an individual's
privacy and their data security.
They can be at risk of hacking, malware,
identity theft, financial fraud,
medical fraud, as well as interpersonal
cybercrime such as cyber bullying.
Data is considered a commodity and is
a primary target of cybercriminals.
It can be accessed illicitly if not
adequately protected by internet
security systems or given away to
scammers unwittingly by individuals
clicking onto bogus links and it can
be used to commit further cybercrimes.
Abraham: Businesses are at risk
from Phishing, DDoS, and malware.
Malware can include different subtypes
such as ransomware, trojans, worms, crypto
miners or spyware as a few examples.
The attack type will often
depend on the type of business
and the technology they use.
It will also be dependent on
what information the hacker
wants to extract or attack.
Cyber attacks can be, as we have already
discussed, by external or insider threats.
Trojan malware enables hackers
to create a backdoor into the
business’ systems and access
business data and login credentials.
Social engineering covers a broad range
of malicious cyber crimes manipulating
users into making security mistakes
or giving away sensitive information
or granting access to resources.
Hackers can inject malicious code into
a website to gain access to information
and login details through keyloggers
and hacking a database of passwords.
Nicole: There has been
a significant growth in
high-profile ransomware campaigns.
Ransomware involves paying a hefty
fee for releasing their data,
however this does not always happen
even when the fee has been paid.
There’s been a recent increase in
ransomware because companies have
started to use cyber insurance.
If a company is affected by ransomware
then the insurance company will pay the
ransom, so cybercriminals know that it
is very likely they will get the money.
There is, however, no guarantee
that the criminals will unencrypt
the data even after they are paid.
Abraham: This can have a knock on
effect, an example of this is when the
AXA insurance firm was ‘ransomwared’
in response to them publicly announcing
they will no longer offer ‘pay
out’ clauses for cyber insurance
It's common now to hear on the news
about cyber attacks from foreign
governments like North Korea, Russia
and China, but threats don't only
come from recognised countries.
Cyber attacks at international
and national state level can
involve major organisations,
national infrastructure, political
parties, military, and governments.
Nicole: The vulnerabilities for nations
are often the same and under the same
threats as businesses, but these can
take on much greater significance as they
can create consequences for everyone.
The threats from nation states and
criminal groups are starting to become
blurred as some nation states use the
'facilities' provided by criminal groups
for their own 'state run' attacks.
Many Russian-speaking cyber groups
are threatening UK interests, but
home-grown cyber criminals are also
becoming more sophisticated and
offering their services to others.
Abraham: The increasing ability
for purchasing 'cyber tools'
has enabled emerging threats
to become established quickly.
Cyber security attacks have become
the new weapon of choice for many
nation states in the effort to
de-stabilise their opponents.
Attacks and threats may be of a political
nature trying to skew the outcomes
of elections, financial gain, digital
surveillance to taking over of military
capabilities and rendering nations
helpless in the face of the threat.